Finding Aid for Office of the Vice President for Research (University of Michigan) publications, 1959-2002 (bulk 1991-2002)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of the Vice President for Research (University of Michigan) publications 1959-2002, 1991-2002
University of Michigan. Office of the Vice-President for Research.
3 linear feet
03156, Bimu, B6, 2
Office overseeing administration of research activity at the University of Michigan. Includes miscellaneous annual reports, brochures, budgets, directories, flyers, histories, invitations, manuals, newsletters, programs, policy statements, and reports. Also includes publications from the Center for Human Growth and Development, Center for the Study of Complex Systems, the Detroit Observatory, Institute for Research on Women and Gender, Jerome B. Wiesner Symposium, Planning Committee on the Merger, and the Substance Abuse Center.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications were first transferred in 1981. The Bentley Library continues to receive publications periodically from the unit (donor no. 5123 ).
The publications are open for research.
Please consult historical note in University of Michigan. Vice President for Research records finding aid immediately preceding the publications finding aid.
The Office of the Vice President for Research Publications (3 linear feet) include annual reports, brochures, budgets, bulletins, ephemera, manuals, newsletters, policy statements, and reports. These publications are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications. The bulk of the publications document the Office of the Vice President for Research, the Center for Human Growth and Development, the Detroit Observatory, and the University of Michigan Substance Abuse Center (UMSAC) which became the University of Michigan Substance Abuse Research Center (UMSARC). Other sub-units under the jurisdiction of the Office of Vice President for Research include the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, University of Michigan Division of Research Development and Administration, University of Michigan Institute of Gerontology, and University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute. For publications from these units the researcher should consult their publications finding aids.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Office of the Vice-President for Research.; University of Michigan. Center for Human Growth and Development.; University of Michigan. Center for the Study of Complex Systems.; University of Michigan. Detroit Observatory.; University of Michigan. Institute for Research on Women and Gender.; Jerome B. Wiesner Symposium (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Planning Committee for the Merger.; University of Michigan. Substance Abuse Center.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Center for Human Growth and Development.; University of Michigan. Center for the Study of Complex Systems.; University of Michigan. Detroit Observatory.; University of Michigan. Institute for Research on Women and Gender.; Jerome B. Wiesner Symposium (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Planning Committee on the Merger.; University of Michigan. Substance Abuse Center.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Directories.; Reports.; Pamphlets.; Budgets.; Flyers.; Histories.; Invitations.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Programs.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Office of the Vice President for Research. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  Unit Publications (1.5 linear feet) include annual reports, brochures, budgets, ephemera including flyers, invitations, posters, and programs, manuals, newsletters, policy statements, presentations and reports. The annual reports include those written for the Board of Regents, under the titles Research Report to the Board of Regents, Report to the Regents, and Research, Scholarship and Creative Activity at the University of Michigan: Annual Report to the Regents, date from 1986 to 1999. These publications highlight the various types of research, detail expenditures, and summarize research proposals done by the faculty and staff of the University of Michigan. Researchers should consult the annual "presentations" made to the Board of Regents by the Vice President for Research for more concise report on research and scholarly activity.
  In 1996 this presentation was entitled Research Expenditures, Sponsored Proposals and Awards. The presentation to the Regents in 1997 was Research and Scholarly Activities: A Presentation to the Regents. Support for Research, Scholarship and Creative Activities: Annual Financial Report, documents the period from 1988 to 1998 and summarizes Office of the Vice President for Research (OVPR) funding allocations by unit, expense category (equipment, salaries, student support, supplies, and travel), academic division, rank of applicant (assistant, associate, and full professors, research scientists, curators, lecturers, and research investigators), gender, and race.
  The 1994 and 1996 Report to the Executive Officers highlight the activities and functions of the OVPR for that year, including initiating information and discussion sessions on responsibility in the conduct and administration of research; conducting open forums to discuss updates in technology, to review new policies toward human subjects, and to assess the impact of Value-Centered Management (VCM) on interdisciplinary research; and developing the OVPR website to provide information about the University of Michigan research program and its policies.
  There are several manuals included in the publications. The Funding for Scholarly Activity published from 1992 through 1993 includes information about funding available from the OVPR, the Rackham School of Graduate Studies and the University Council of International Academic Affairs. Research and Scholarship Support Available from the Office of the Vice President for Research published in 1986 has similar information from the OVPR only. The 1982 and 1987 Intellectual Property Manual define intellectual property and describe the university's policy, procedures, and the inventor's responsibilities to the university as does the related 1978 Patent Manual. University of Michigan Research and Development Resources: A Guide for Businesses published in 1993, serves as a ready reference guide to the resources that the university can offer small businesses including special conferences, economic development advice, affiliate programs and partnerships, and placement offices and co-op education programs. Newsletters such as the single issue of OVPR Newsletter give the latest news in the vice president's office in 1991 and the OVPR Bulletin dating from 1994 to 1996 describe not only what is going on in the area of research at the university, but also how Homer Neal, Vice President for Research, saw issues in the area of research, such as integrity of scholarship, financial conflicts of interest, accountability, and federal funding. The policy statements include an Interim Policy Statement on The Integrity of Scholarship and Investigating Allegations of Misconduct in the Pursuit of Scholarship and Research published in 1986, under the leadership of Linda Wilson, to encourage "ethical practices in scholarship." In 1993 Vice President Homer Neal issued a Policy and Program Update for Primary Research Staff. This update pulled policy statements, from the Board of Regents Bylaws, the Standard Practice Guide, the Affirmative Action Office, the Faculty and Staff Assistance Program, and the Family Care Resources Office, together in one place as a ready-reference for primary researchers on campus.
  The reports include a 1972 report Indirect Costs of Research, from the Office of the Vice President for Research at the request of the Commission of Resource Allocation to clarify the policies and procedures governing reimbursement of indirect costs to the university. In 1986 the Technology Transfer at the University of Michigan: Reality from Vision; the Plan that is Working was released. This report discusses the work of the Intellectual Property Office. Environmental and Hazardous Substances Research, published in 1990, describes research by the Michigan Universities Consortium for Hazardous Waste Management. This consortium of researchers from the University of Michigan and Michigan State University focused on the multidisciplinary activities needed to conduct research on the complex hazardous substances problems in the state. The report includes a directory of researchers, their research projects, and funding sources, bulletins describing graduate programs, and a breakdown of research funding.
  - Annual Reports
    - Quarterly Report to the Executive Officers, 1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Report to the Executive Officers, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Report to the Regents, 1992-1997, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Research Expenditures, Sponsored Proposals and Awards, 1993-1997, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Research Proposals, Awards and Expenditures, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Research Report to the Board of Regents, 1986-1991, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Research, Scholarship and Creative Activity at the University of Michigan: Annual Report to the Regents, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Sponsored Proposals and Awards: Research Expenditures, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Support for Research, Scholarship, and Creative Activities, 1988-1998, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - 1960 1989-1999 (Box 1)
  - Budgets
    - Budget Proposal (Box 2)
      - 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Flyers
    - 1988-1994 (Box 2)
  - Humor
    - Excerpts from the Middle English Dictionary, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Invitations
    - 1980-1994 (Box 2)
  - Manuals
    - A-21 Guidance for Principal Investigators, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Funding for Scholarly Activities, 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Intellectual Property Manual, 1982, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Patent Manual, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Research and Development Resources: A Guide for Businesses, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Research and Scholarship Support Available from the Office of the Vice President for Research, 1986 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Research and Development Resources: A Guide for Small Businesses, undated (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - OVPR Bulletin, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - OVPR Newsletter, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Policy Statements
    - The Integrity of Scholarship and Investigating Allegations of Misconduct in the Pursuit of Scholarship and Research, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Policy and Program Update, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Posters
    - 1994-1997 undated (Box 2)
  - Presentations
    - Research and Scholarly Activities: A Presentation to the Regents, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Research Expenditures, Sponsored Proposals and Awards, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Programs
    - 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - Environmental and Hazardous Substance Research, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Indirect Costs of Research, 1972 (Box 2)
    - A Michigan Tradition: Research and Undergraduate Education, June and July 1987 (Box 2)
    - Technology Transfer at the University of Michigan: Reality from Vision; the Plan that is Working, 1986 (Box 2)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs, and organizations reporting to the Vice President for Research. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
  Arts and Citizenship Program
  Biophysics Research Division
  Center for Statistical Consultation and Research
  Committee to Study the Office of Vice President for Research
  Center for the Study of Complex Systems
  Faculty Committee on VCM and Research Excellence
  Human Subjects Review Committee
  Imagining America
  Middle English Dictionary
  Office of Technology Transfer
  Office of the Business Manager for Sponsored Research
  Office of Vice President for Research Faculty Committee on Value Centered Management and Research Excellence
  Presidential Initiatives Fund
  Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine
  University Committee on Use and Care of Animals
  The Sub-Unit Publications series (1.5 linear feet) includes single folders of publications from the following sub-units of the Vice President for Research:
  These publications may include announcements, annual reports, brochures, directories, festschrift, flyers, histories, invitations, manuals, newsletters, programs, proceedings, reports, and statistics.
  Other units reporting to the Vice President for Research, who have a greater quantity of publications held by the Bentley Historical Library, include the Center for Human Growth and Development, the Center for the Study of Complex Systems, the Detroit Observatory, the Institute for Research on Women and Gender, Jerome B. Wiesner Symposium, Planning Committee for the Merger (of duties between the Vice President for Research and the Dean of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies), and the Substance Abuse Center.
  There are twelve folders of publications from the Center for Human Growth and Development including annual reports spanning from 1980 to 1998, brochures, calendars, and flyers. The manual entitled Resource Guide for Development and Aging published in 1989 is also in this sub-unit. There are newsletters from 1972 to 1973, and 1981. The 1963 proposal for the center and the presentation to the Regents is also included. There is a single 1994 report entitled Longitudinal Studies of Human Behavior detailing the various studies conducted by the Center for Human Growth and Development.
  The Center for the Study of Complex Systems contains four folders of publications including a festschrift honoring John C. Holland published in 1999. There are also folders of flyers advertising John C. Holland's short course in the fall of 2001 and seminars sponsored by the center. In 2001 an external review of the Center for the Study of Complex Systems was issued.
  The Detroit Observatory publications are divided into nine folders. The bulk of the publications are reports dating from 1996 to 1997 describing the restoration of the Observatory. There is also a history by director and curator Patricia Whitesell entitled A Creation of His Own: Tappan's Detroit Observatory, published in 1998. There are also folders of development brochures from 1996 and flyers advertising lectures and programs sponsored by the Detroit Observatory from 1999 to 2002.
  The Institute for Research on Women and Gender (IRWG) publications are included in five folders. There is a brochure, entitled Stories from Lane Hall, compiled in 2000 to celebrate the new home of the institute and the Women's Studies Program. There is a folder of e-mail printout calendars describing the activities sponsored by IRWG. There are also newsletters, News from the Institute for Research on Women and Gender at the University of Michigan, covering the period from 1996 to 1997 and posters, dating from 1997 to 2002, advertising speakers sponsored by the institute.
  The Jerome B. Wiesner Symposium was created to honor the memory of a noted alumnus of the university and to continue the dialogue on the future of the government/university partnership in research. The four folders include programs documenting the symposium from 1996 to 1999. The Bentley Historical Library has published copies of the proceedings from the 1996 symposium The Future of the Government/University Partnership and the 1999 forum, New Integrations of Research, Scholarship, and Undergraduate Education. There is also a copy of the 1999 workshop abstracts.
  In 1983, President Shapiro recommended that a committee be created to analyze the possibility of merging the offices of Vice President for Research and Dean of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies. The Planning Committee for the Merger was created, as well as two subcommittees. There are three reports found in the publications of the Vice President for Research. In the end the merger was not implemented.
  The Substance Abuse Center coordinates an interdisciplinary effort to stimulate, integrate, and coordinate the study of psychoactive substance abuse, working to understand the mechanisms and develop policies for prevention of abuse. (A Self Study Report, vol. 1, p. 4) The six folders of publications for this sub-unit cover the period from 1989 to 1994. Included is a 1989 campus-wide directory listing the various substance abuse-related research activities, prevention and treatment centers, and educational programs offered by the various university units. The 1986 report entitled Feasibility of Establishing a Substance Abuse Center for Research, Education and Service at the University of Michigan includes the proposal for the center. The center's name changed in 1995 to Substance Abuse Research Center to reflect its primary function on campus. In 1996 the research center developed a two volume Self Study Report including an in-depth report on the center's mission statement, activities, organization, budget, annual reports from 1988 to 1993, organization chart, resumes of staff members with their job descriptions, and history.
  - Arts and Citizenship Program undated (Box 2)
  - Biophysics Research Division 1989 (Box 2)
  - Center for Human Growth and Development 1963-2001, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Center for Statistical Consultation and Research undated (Box 2)
  - Center for the Study of Complex Systems 1999-2002, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Committee to Study the Office of Vice President for Research 1971 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Observatory 1994-2002, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Faculty Committee on VCM [Value Centered Management] and Research Excellence 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Human Subjects Review Committee 1997 (Box 3)
  - Imagining America 2000 (Box 3)
  - Institute for Research on Women and Gender 1996-2002, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Jerome B. Wiesner Symposium 1996-1999, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Middle English Dictionary 1996 (Box 3)
  - Office of the Business Manager for Sponsored Research 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Office of Technology Transfer 1995-1996, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Planning Committee for the Merge 1983-1984, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Presidential Initiatives Fund 1994/95 (Box 3)
  - Substance Abuse Center, 1986-1994, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Substance Abuse Research Center 1996 (Box 3)
  - Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine 1984 (Box 3)
  - University Committee on Use and Care of Animals 1997 (Box 3)
Related Material:
For additional manuscript records and publications on research at the university, the researcher should search the Bentley Library holdings in the on-line (MIRLYN) catalogs under the following University of Michigan headings:
Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project
University of Michigan. Division of Research Development and Administration
University of Michigan. Institute for Gerontology
University of Michigan. Transportation Research Institute